<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>CompressedStream</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Core</module>
    <comment>Acts as a proxy for decompressing and compressing data streams between objects.</comment>
    <fileDescription>GZip File</fileDescription>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>6e56d1fb</id>
    <idstring>COMPRESSEDSTREAM</idstring>
    <category>Data</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 1996-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>Use the CompressedStream class to compress and decompress data on the fly without the need for a temporary storage area.  The default compression algorithm is DEFLATE with gzip header data.  It is compatible with common command-line tools such as gzip.</p>
<p>To decompress data, set the <fl>Input</fl> field with a source object that supports the Read() action, such as a <class name="File">File</class>. Repeatedly reading from the CompressedStream will automatically handle the decompression process.  If the decompressed size of the incoming data is defined in the source header, it will be reflected in the <fl>Size</fl> field.</p>
<p>To compress data, set the <fl>Output</fl> field with a source object that supports the Write() action, such as a <class name="File">File</class>. Repeatedly writing to the CompressedStream with raw data will automatically handle the compression process for you. Once all of the data has been written, call the <action>Write</action> action with a null empty <code>Buffer</code> to finalise the stream.  In Tiri, call <code>acWrite(nil)</code>.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="../compression/">class_compressed_stream.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Read</name>
      <comment>Decompress data from the input stream and write it to the supplied buffer.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acRead(*Object, std::span&lt;int8_t&gt; Buffer, INT *Result)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err, Result:num = Object.acRead(Buffer:array)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="std::span&lt;int8_t&gt;" name="Buffer">A mutable buffer that will receive the data.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Result">The Read action will write this parameter with the total number of bytes read into the Buffer.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Reset</name>
      <comment>Reset the state of the stream.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acReset(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acReset()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Resetting a CompressedStream returns it to the same state as that when first initialised.  Note that this does not affect the state of the object referenced via <fl>Input</fl> or <fl>Output</fl>, so it may be necessary for the client to reset referenced objects separately.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Seek</name>
      <comment>For use in decompressing streams only.  Seeks to a position within the stream.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acSeek(*Object, DOUBLE Offset, INT Position)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acSeek(Offset:num, Position:SEEK)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Offset">The desired offset to seek to, relative to the Position parameter.</param>
        <param type="POS" name="Position">The position that defines the starting point for Offset.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Write</name>
      <comment>Compress raw data in a buffer and write it to the Output object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acWrite(*Object, std::span&lt;const int8_t&gt; Buffer, INT *Result)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err, Result:num = Object.acWrite(Buffer:str)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="std::span&lt;const int8_t&gt;" name="Buffer">A buffer containing the data that will be written to the object.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Result">This parameter with be updated with the total number of bytes written from the Buffer.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>Format</name>
      <comment>The format of the compressed stream.  The default is GZIP.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type lookup="CF">CF</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="CF"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Input</name>
      <comment>An input object that will supply data for decompression.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type>OBJECTPTR</type>
      <description>
<p>To create a stream that decompresses data from a compressed source, set the Input field with a reference to an object that will provide the source data.  It is most common for the source object to be a <class name="File">File</class> type, however any class that supports the Read() action is permitted.</p>
<p>The source object must be in a readable state.  The Input field is mutually exclusive to the <fl>Output</fl> field.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Output</name>
      <comment>A target object that will receive data compressed by the stream.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type>OBJECTPTR</type>
      <description>
<p>To create a stream that compresses data to a target object, set the Output field with an object reference.  It is most common for the target object to be a <class name="File">File</class> type, however any class that supports the Write() action is permitted.</p>
<p>The target object must be in a writeable state.  The Output field is mutually exclusive to the <fl>Input</fl> field.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Size</name>
      <comment>The uncompressed size of the input source, if known.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT64</type>
      <description>
<p>The Size field will reflect the uncompressed size of the input source, if this can be determined from the header. In the case of GZIP decompression, the size will not be known until the parser has consumed the header. This means that at least one call to the <action>Read</action> action is required before the Size is known.</p>
<p>If the size is unknown, a value of <code>-1</code> is returned.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>TotalOutput</name>
      <comment>A live counter of total bytes that have been output by the stream.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT64</type>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="CF" comment="Compression stream formats">
      <const name="DEFLATE">The 'deflate' format</const>
      <const name="GZIP">The 'gzip' format</const>
      <const name="ZLIB">The 'zlib' format</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
