<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>DisplacementFX</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Vector</module>
    <comment>Applies the displacement map filter effect.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>e3c51df2</id>
    <idstring>DISPLACEMENTFX</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2010-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>This filter effect uses the pixel values from the image from Mix to spatially displace the image from Input. This is the transformation to be performed:</p>
<pre>P'(x,y) &lt;- P(x + Scale * (XC(x,y) - 0.5), y + Scale * (YC(x,y) - 0.5))
</pre>
<p>where <code>P(x,y)</code> is the Input image, and <code>P'(x,y)</code> is the Target.  <code>XC(x,y)</code> and <code>YC(x,y)</code> are the component values of the channel designated by the <fl>XChannel</fl> and <fl>YChannel</fl>.  For example, to use the red component of Mix to control displacement in <code>X</code> and the green component to control displacement in <code>Y</code>, set <fl>XChannel</fl> to <code>CMP::RED</code> and <fl>YChannel</fl> to <code>CMP::GREEN</code>.</p>
<p>The displacement map defines the inverse of the mapping performed.</p>
<p>The Input image is to remain premultiplied for this filter effect.  The calculations using the pixel values from Mix are performed using non-premultiplied colour values.  If the image from Mix consists of premultiplied colour values, those values are automatically converted into non-premultiplied colour values before performing this operation.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="filters/">filter_displacement.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Draw</name>
      <comment>Render the effect to the target bitmap.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acDraw(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acDraw(X:num, Y:num, Width:num, Height:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="INT" name="X">The X position of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Y">The Y position of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Width">The width of the region to be drawn.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Height">The height of the region to be drawn.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>ResampleMethod</name>
      <comment>The resample algorithm to use for transforming the source image.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type lookup="VSM">VSM</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="VSM"/>
<p>Currently <code>NEIGHBOUR</code> and <code>BILINEAR</code> are supported. Other resample methods fall back to bilinear filtering.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Scale</name>
      <comment>Displacement scale factor.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The amount is expressed in the coordinate system established by <class name="VectorFilter" field="PrimitiveUnits">VectorFilter.PrimitiveUnits</class> on the parent <class name="VectorFilter">VectorFilter</class>. When the value of this field is 0, this operation has no effect on the source image.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>XChannel</name>
      <comment>X axis channel selection.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type lookup="CMP">CMP</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="CMP"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>XMLDef</name>
      <comment>Returns an SVG compliant XML string that describes the effect.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
      <tags>caller-owns-result</tags>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>YChannel</name>
      <comment>Y axis channel selection.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type lookup="CMP">CMP</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="CMP"/>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="CMP" comment="Component selection for RemapFX methods.">
      <const name="ALL">All colour channels.</const>
      <const name="ALPHA">The alpha channel.</const>
      <const name="BLUE">The blue colour channel.</const>
      <const name="GREEN">The green colour channel.</const>
      <const name="RED">The red colour channel.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="VSM">
      <const name="AUTO">The default option is chosen by the system.  This will typically be <code>BILINEAR</code>, but slow machines may switch to nearest neighbour and high speed machines could use more advanced methods.</const>
      <const name="BESSEL">Uses a broad Bessel filter that can preserve detail during resampling, but is slower than the smaller-kernel methods.</const>
      <const name="BICUBIC">Produces a similar result to <code>BILINEAR</code> at a slightly higher CPU cost and a marginally sharper after-effect.</const>
      <const name="BILINEAR">Bilinear is a common algorithm that produces a reasonable quality image quickly.</const>
      <const name="BLACKMAN">Five times slower than <code>BILINEAR</code>, the final result will be less sharp than SINC.</const>
      <const name="GAUSSIAN">Uses a Gaussian filter that softens the result, reducing aliasing at the cost of sharp edge detail.</const>
      <const name="KAISER">Uses a Kaiser-windowed filter, giving smooth interpolation with low ringing and a cost close to <code>BILINEAR</code>.</const>
      <const name="LANCZOS">This well known algorithm may serve as a point of comparison for evaluating the results of other methods.  It shares characteristics with <code>SINC</code> and <code>BLACKMAN</code>.</const>
      <const name="MITCHELL">Uses a Mitchell-Netravali filter, balancing sharpness and smoothness at a cost similar to <code>BICUBIC</code>.</const>
      <const name="NEIGHBOUR">Nearest neighbour is the fastest sampler at the cost of poor quality.</const>
      <const name="QUADRIC">Uses a quadratic filter with a modest kernel, giving smoother results than <code>BILINEAR</code> with limited extra cost.</const>
      <const name="SINC">Five times slower than <code>BILINEAR</code>, the final result is of very good quality.</const>
      <const name="SPLINE16">About twice as slow as <code>BILINEAR</code>, this method samples a 4x4 area and produces a considerably better result, and is a good choice for enlarging images without producing artifacts when contrasting colours are present.</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
