<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>GradientDistal</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Vector</module>
    <comment>Signed distance field colour gradient paint server.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>e8d90a9c</id>
    <idstring>GRADIENTDISTAL</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2010-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>GradientDistal shades inward and outward from the target vector path outline.  The path outline is pinned to the centre of the colour ramp, <code>Radius</code> controls exterior padding, and <code>InnerRadius</code> controls interior fade-out.</p>
<p>The base <class name="Gradient" field="SpreadMethod">Gradient.SpreadMethod</class> field selects how the exterior fade behaves beyond the first cycle, where one cycle spans the <code>Radius</code> distance:</p>
<list type="bullet">
<li>
<code>PAD</code> (the default) fades once over the <code>Radius</code> distance and then stops, producing the classic glow or halo.</li>
<li>
<code>REPEAT</code> tiles the fade outward as a sawtooth: at the end of each <code>Radius</code> cycle the alpha and colour restart at
full strength, repeating until the parent area is filled.</li>
<li>
<code>REFLECT</code> tiles the fade outward as a triangle wave: each cycle alternates direction, ramping the alpha back up
from zero before fading again, repeating until the parent area is filled.</li>
</list>
<p>Setting <fl>OuterFall</fl> to <code>GFALL::OPAQUE</code> holds the exterior alpha at full strength rather than tapering it, so with <code>REPEAT</code> or <code>REFLECT</code> the full colour ramp is painted solidly out to the parent edge with no fade between tiles.  Under <code>PAD</code> the alpha still cuts to transparent at the padding edge as usual.</p>
<p>This gradient operates exclusively in <code>BOUNDING_BOX</code> space.  If <class name="Gradient" field="Units">Gradient.Units</class> is set to <code>USERSPACE</code> it will be reset to <code>BOUNDING_BOX</code> during initialisation.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="painters/">gradient_distal.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>Floor</name>
      <comment>Colour ramp floor for distal gradients.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The Floor value is used as the floor for distal gradient colour values.  It has a valid range of <code>0 &lt;= Floor &lt; Multiplier</code>; the constraint against <fl>Multiplier</fl> is enforced at initialisation.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>InnerFall</name>
      <comment>Selects the alpha fall-off curve for the interior fade.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>InnerFall controls the shape of the interior alpha fade that runs from the path outline inward to <code>InnerRadius</code>.  The default is <code>GFALL::SMOOTHSTEP</code>.  The fade is only visible when <code>InnerRadius</code> is non-zero; with a zero InnerRadius the interior remains fully opaque and the curve has no effect.</p>
<p>Setting InnerFall to <code>GFALL::CLEAR</code> disables the interior entirely, rendering it fully transparent irrespective of <code>InnerRadius</code>.  This is useful for producing an exterior-only halo with no fill inside the path outline.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>InnerRadius</name>
      <comment>The size of the inner radius for distal gradients.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>The InnerRadius defines the extent of the interior fade-out for distal gradients.  If zero, the interior of the target shape is fully rendered.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Multiplier</name>
      <comment>Colour ramp multiplier for distal gradients.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The Multiplier value acts as a multiplier for distal gradient colour values.  It has a valid range of <code>.01 &lt; Multiplier &lt; 10</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>OuterFall</name>
      <comment>Selects the alpha fall-off curve for the exterior fade.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>OuterFall controls the shape of the exterior alpha fade that runs from the path outline outward to the padding edge defined by <code>Radius</code>.  The default is <code>GFALL::SMOOTHSTEP</code>.  Faster curves such as <code>GFALL::QUADRATIC</code> and <code>GFALL::CUBIC</code> produce a tighter halo, while <code>GFALL::SMOOTHSTEP</code> holds the inner half bright for a wider glow.</p>
<p>Setting OuterFall to <code>GFALL::CLEAR</code> disables the exterior entirely, rendering it fully transparent so that only the interior half of the gradient is drawn.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Radius</name>
      <comment>Exterior margin around the target path.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>The Radius value controls how much exterior padding is added around the target path so that the exterior half of the signed distance colour ramp remains visible.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="GFALL" comment="Gradient fall-off options.">
      <const name="CLEAR">Disables the gradient.</const>
      <const name="CUBIC">Cubic fall-off - very tight glow hugging the outline.</const>
      <const name="LINEAR">Linear fall-off (even taper).</const>
      <const name="OPAQUE">No fall-off.</const>
      <const name="QUADRATIC">Quadratic fall-off - fast drop, thin tail — natural glow.</const>
      <const name="SMOOTHSTEP">Smoothstep fall-off - S-curve; brightest, holds the inner half.</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
