<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>GradientDistal</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Vector</module>
    <comment>Signed distance field colour gradient paint server.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>e8d90a9c</id>
    <idstring>GRADIENTDISTAL</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2010-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>GradientDistal shades inward and outward from the target vector path outline.  The path outline is pinned to the centre of the colour ramp, <code>Radius</code> controls exterior padding, and <code>InnerRadius</code> controls interior fade-out.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="painters/">gradient_distal.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>Floor</name>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>InnerFall</name>
      <comment>Selects the alpha fall-off curve for the interior fade.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>InnerFall controls the shape of the interior alpha fade that runs from the path outline inward to <code>InnerRadius</code>.  The default is <code>GFALL::SMOOTHSTEP</code>.  The fade is only visible when <code>InnerRadius</code> is non-zero; with a zero InnerRadius the interior remains fully opaque and this field has no effect.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>InnerRadius</name>
      <comment>The size of the inner radius for distal gradients.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The InnerRadius defines the extent of the interior fade-out for distal gradients.  If zero, the interior of the target shape is fully rendered.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Multiplier</name>
      <comment>Colour ramp multiplier for distal gradients.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The Multiplier value acts as a multiplier for distal gradient colour values.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>OuterFall</name>
      <comment>Selects the alpha fall-off curve for the exterior fade.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>OuterFall controls the shape of the exterior alpha fade that runs from the path outline outward to the padding edge defined by <code>Radius</code>.  The default is <code>GFALL::SMOOTHSTEP</code>.  Faster curves such as <code>GFALL::QUADRATIC</code> and <code>GFALL::CUBIC</code> produce a tighter halo, while <code>GFALL::SMOOTHSTEP</code> holds the inner half bright for a wider glow.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Radius</name>
      <comment>Exterior margin around the target path.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The Radius value controls how much exterior padding is added around the target path so that the exterior half of the signed distance colour ramp remains visible.</p>
<p>Floor: Colour ramp floor for distal gradients.</p>
<p>The Floor value is used as the floor for distal gradient colour values.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
