<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>LZMAStream</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>LZMA</module>
    <comment>Decompresses raw LZMA1 data streams.</comment>
    <fileDescription>GZip File</fileDescription>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>ea1b1936</id>
    <idstring>LZMASTREAM</idstring>
    <category>Data</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2024-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The LZMAStream class extends <class name="CompressedStream">CompressedStream</class> with support for decoding raw LZMA1 streams.  It is provided by the separate <code>LZMA</code> module so that the Core remains free of an LZMA dependency; only builds that require LZMA pull the module in.</p>
<p>LZMAStream is decode-only and is instantiated directly rather than being selected through a <class name="CompressedStream" field="Format">CompressedStream.Format</class> option on the base class.  To decompress a stream, set the <class name="CompressedStream" field="Input">CompressedStream.Input</class> field with a source object that supports the Read() action (such as a <class name="File">File</class>) and set the required <fl>UncompressedSize</fl> field to the exact number of decompressed bytes expected. Repeatedly reading from the LZMAStream then yields the decompressed data:</p>
<pre>local lz = obj.new('lzmastream', { input=file, uncompressedSize=body_size })
local err, len = lz.acRead(buffer)
</pre>
<p>The class decodes a raw LZMA1 stream consisting of a 5-byte properties header followed by the compressed data.  It does not parse the <code>.lzma</code>/<code>.alone</code> 13-byte header or the <code>.xz</code> container; callers are responsible for any outer framing.  Because raw LZMA1 streams may lack a reliable end marker, <fl>UncompressedSize</fl> is used to bound the output: decoding completes when exactly that many bytes have been produced, and an end marker or exhausted input encountered before that point is reported as a decompression error.</p>
<p>The inherited <class name="CompressedStream" field="Format">CompressedStream.Format</class> field has no meaning for this class and is ignored.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file>lzma.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Read</name>
      <comment>Decompress data from the input stream and write it to the supplied buffer.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acRead(*Object, APTR Buffer, INT Length, INT *Result)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err, Result:num = Object.acRead(Buffer:str, Length:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="APTR" name="Buffer">Points a buffer that will receive the data.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Length">The total number of bytes to read from the object.  This value cannot exceed the size of the Buffer.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Result">The Read action will write this parameter with the total number of bytes read into the Buffer.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>The Read() action decodes the raw LZMA1 stream supplied via <class name="CompressedStream" field="Input">CompressedStream.Input</class>, writing up to <code>Length</code> decompressed bytes into the caller's buffer.  Decoding is bounded by <fl>UncompressedSize</fl>; once that many bytes have been produced, subsequent reads return zero bytes.  Truncated input, a premature end marker or output that would exceed <fl>UncompressedSize</fl> are reported as <code>ERR::Decompression</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Reset</name>
      <comment>Reset the state of the stream.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acReset(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acReset()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Resetting an LZMAStream returns it to the same state as when first initialised.  This does not affect the state of the object referenced via <class name="CompressedStream" field="Input">CompressedStream.Input</class>, so the client may need to reset or re-seek that object separately.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Write</name>
      <comment>Not supported.  LZMAStream is decode-only.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acWrite(*Object, APTR Buffer, INT Length, INT Result)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err, Result:num = Object.acWrite(Buffer:str, Length:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="APTR" name="Buffer">A buffer containing the data that will be written to the object.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Length">The total number of bytes to write to the object.</param>
        <param type="INT" name="Result">This parameter with be updated with the total number of bytes written from the Buffer.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>UncompressedSize</name>
      <comment>The exact number of bytes expected from the decompressed stream.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT64</type>
      <description>
<p>This field is required prior to initialisation.  Raw LZMA1 streams may not carry a reliable end marker, so the value is used to bound decoding: the stream completes when exactly this many bytes have been produced, and an end marker or exhausted input encountered beforehand is reported as a decompression error.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
