<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>Pointer</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Display</module>
    <comment>Tracks pointer position, button state and cursor image selection.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>177166ee</id>
    <idstring>POINTER</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2003-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The Pointer class represents the active pointing device used by the display system.  It tracks global pointer coordinates, the surface and object under the hot spot, button state, drag state and the cursor image currently being shown to the user.</p>
<p>On hosted systems such as Windows and X11, pointer movement and cursor images are synchronised with the host windowing system.  On native displays, the display module is responsible for drawing and managing the cursor directly.</p>
<p>A system-wide pointer object named <code>SystemPointer</code> is created automatically.  Applications and module code should use this shared object, usually via <function module="Display">AccessPointer</function>, when reading pointer state or changing cursor behaviour.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file>class_pointer.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>DataFeed</name>
      <comment>Sends device input events to the pointer.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acDataFeed(*Object, OBJECTID Object, DATA Datatype, std::span&lt;const int8_t&gt; Buffer)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acDataFeed(Object:obj, Datatype:DATA, Buffer:str)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="OBJECTID" name="Object">Must refer to the unique ID of the object that you represent. If you do not represent an object, set this parameter to the current task ID.</param>
        <param type="DATA" name="Datatype" lookup="DATA">The type of data being sent.</param>
        <param type="std::span&lt;const int8_t&gt;" name="Buffer">The data being sent to the target object.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>Use DataFeed with the <code>DATA::DEVICE_INPUT</code> data type to submit one or more <code>dcDeviceInput</code> records to a pointer object. The supplied records are interpreted in the same way as input received from host or native hardware.</p>
<p>Button presses are stateful.  If a submitted record presses a button, the client must later submit the corresponding release record so click, drag and repeat handling can return to a consistent state.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Hide</name>
      <comment>Hides the pointer cursor.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acHide(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acHide()</tiriPrototype>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Move</name>
      <comment>Moves the pointer by a relative offset.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMove(*Object, DOUBLE DeltaX, DOUBLE DeltaY, DOUBLE DeltaZ)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMove(DeltaX:num, DeltaY:num, DeltaZ:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaX">The number of units to move along the X axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaY">The number of units to move along the Y axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaZ">The number of units to move along the Z axis.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>The Move action adjusts the current <fl>X</fl> and <fl>Y</fl> coordinates by the supplied delta values.  It applies the movement immediately by forwarding the resulting position to <action>MoveToPoint</action>.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>MoveToPoint</name>
      <comment>Moves the pointer to an absolute location.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMoveToPoint(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Z, MTF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMoveToPoint(X:num, Y:num, Z:num, Flags:MTF)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="X">The new X position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Y">The new Y position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Z">The new Z position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="MTF" name="Flags" lookup="MTF">Set the relevant MTF flag for each provided parameter.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>The MoveToPoint action changes the pointer's <fl>X</fl> and <fl>Y</fl> coordinates immediately.  It updates the host cursor position where supported, refreshes the object under the hot spot and notifies subscribers to MoveToPoint with the final coordinates.</p>
<p>This action is intended for programmatic repositioning.  Hardware input is normally delivered through DataFeed and is translated into input events for the affected surface or object.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Refresh</name>
      <comment>Refreshes the pointer's target and cursor image.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acRefresh(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acRefresh()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>This action recalculates the object under the pointer hot spot and reapplies any cursor image selected by the underlying surface.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Reset</name>
      <comment>Restores user-adjustable pointer settings to their defaults.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acReset(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acReset()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>This action resets movement speed, acceleration, double-click interval, maximum speed and wheel speed.  It does not move the pointer or clear the current cursor ownership state.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>SaveToObject</name>
      <comment>Saves pointer preferences to another object.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acSaveToObject(*Object, OBJECTID Dest, CLASSID ClassID)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acSaveToObject(Dest:obj, ClassID:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="OBJECTID" name="Dest">Refers to an object that will receive the encoded data.</param>
        <param type="CLASSID" name="ClassID">Can refer to a derived class that should be used when encoding the data.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>This action writes the current speed, acceleration, double-click interval, maximum speed, wheel speed and button order to the destination object in configuration format.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Show</name>
      <comment>Shows the pointer cursor.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acShow(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acShow()</tiriPrototype>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>Acceleration</name>
      <comment>The rate of acceleration for relative pointer movement.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>This field affects relative pointer movement before the final coordinates are applied.  It is normally treated as a user preference, because suitable acceleration values depend on the input device and user expectations.</p>
<p>Hosted display drivers may apply their own pointer acceleration before events reach the display module, so this field is not always relevant in hosted environments.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Anchor</name>
      <comment>Can refer to a surface that the pointer has been anchored to.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>If the pointer has been anchored to a surface through <function module="Display">SetCursor</function>, this field refers to the surface that receives anchored movement events.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Bitmap</name>
      <comment>Refers to bitmap in which custom cursor images can be drawn.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type class="Bitmap">*Bitmap</type>
      <description>
<p>The pointer graphic can be changed to a custom image by drawing into this <class name="Bitmap">Bitmap</class> and selecting <code>PTC::CUSTOM</code> with <function module="Display">SetCustomCursor</function>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ButtonOrder</name>
      <comment>Defines the order in which mouse buttons are interpreted.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
      <description>
<p>This field defines how physical pointer buttons are mapped to logical button positions when pressed.  It can be used to remap a right-handed device for left-handed use, or to normalise unusual button layouts.</p>
<p>The default button order is <code>123456789AB</code>.  The left, right and middle buttons are defined as <code>1</code>, <code>2</code> and <code>3</code> respectively.  Additional buttons are assigned by the device.</p>
<p>Buttons may be referenced more than once.  For example, <code>111</code> maps the first three physical buttons to the logical left button.</p>
<p>Changes to this field will have an immediate impact on the pointing device's behaviour.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ButtonState</name>
      <comment>Indicates the current button-press state.</comment>
      <access read="G">Get</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field returns the current pointer button state as bit flags after <fl>ButtonOrder</fl> mapping has been applied.  A set bit indicates that the corresponding logical button is being held down.</p>
<p>The first three bits represent left, right and middle button state respectively, with the left button at bit position zero.  Additional buttons are supported, but their order depends on the device and the active <fl>ButtonOrder</fl> setting.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>ClickSlop</name>
      <comment>A leniency value that assists in determining if the user intended to click or drag.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>ClickSlop defines the allowed pointer movement, in pixels, before a press-and-release sequence is treated as a drag rather than a click.  The same tolerance is used when deciding whether a second click is close enough to qualify as a double-click.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>CursorID</name>
      <comment>Identifies the active cursor image.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type lookup="PTC">PTC</type>
      <description>
<p>This field stores the cursor image currently selected for the pointer.  Use <function module="Display">SetCursor</function> or <function module="Display">SetCustomCursor</function> to change the cursor after initialisation.</p>
<types lookup="PTC"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>CursorOwner</name>
      <comment>The object that currently owns the cursor state.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>If the cursor is currently locked by an owner, this field refers to that owner's object ID.  Cursor ownership is managed by <function module="Display">SetCursor</function> and released with <function module="Display">RestoreCursor</function>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DoubleClick</name>
      <comment>The maximum interval between two clicks for a double click to be recognised.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>A double-click is recognised when two presses of the same logical button occur within this interval.  The value is measured in seconds and defaults to the user's pointer preference.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DragItem</name>
      <comment>The currently dragged item, as defined by <function module="Display">StartCursorDrag</function>.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>When a drag-and-drop operation is active, this field contains the custom item number supplied to <function module="Display">StartCursorDrag</function>. At all other times it is zero.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DragSource</name>
      <comment>The object managing the current drag operation, as defined by <function module="Display">StartCursorDrag</function>.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>When a drag-and-drop operation is active, this field refers to the object managing the source data.  At all other times it is zero.</p>
<p>Item dragging is managed by <function module="Display">StartCursorDrag</function>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Flags</name>
      <comment>Optional flags.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type lookup="PF">PF</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="PF"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Input</name>
      <comment>Declares the I/O object to read movement from.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>This field records an alternate object intended to supply pointer movement.  Input records delivered to the pointer must use the same <code>DATA::DEVICE_INPUT</code> format accepted by <action>DataFeed</action>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>MaxSpeed</name>
      <comment>Restricts the maximum speed of a pointer's movement.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field limits the maximum relative movement applied to the pointer during a single update.  Values assigned to the field are clamped to the supported range.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>OverObject</name>
      <comment>Readable field that gives the ID of the object under the pointer.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>This field returns the object directly under the pointer hot spot.  <code>NULL</code> can be returned if there is no surface object under the pointer.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>OverX</name>
      <comment>The horizontal position of the pointer with respect to the object underneath the hot spot.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>This field gives the horizontal position of the pointer hot spot relative to <fl>OverObject</fl>.  It can be read when handling input to determine the object-local coordinate affected by a click, wheel or movement event.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>OverY</name>
      <comment>The vertical position of the pointer with respect to the object underneath the hot spot.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>This field gives the vertical position of the pointer hot spot relative to <fl>OverObject</fl>.  It can be read together with <fl>OverX</fl> to determine the object-local coordinate affected by pointer input.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>OverZ</name>
      <comment>The position of the Pointer within an object.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>This field is reserved for interfaces that can report pointer depth.  It reflects the pointer coordinate on the Z axis relative to the object under the hot spot.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Restrict</name>
      <comment>Refers to a surface when the pointer is restricted.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>If the pointer has been restricted to a surface through <function module="Display">SetCursor</function>, this field refers to that surface.  If the pointer is not restricted, this field is zero.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Speed</name>
      <comment>Speed multiplier for pointer movement.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>This field controls the relative movement multiplier, expressed as a percentage.  Values below 100 reduce movement, while values above 100 increase movement.  <fl>MaxSpeed</fl> is applied as a separate upper limit.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Surface</name>
      <comment>The top-most surface that is under the pointer's hot spot.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>OBJECTID</type>
      <description>
<p>This field refers to the top-most <class name="Surface">Surface</class> under the pointer hot spot.  It is automatically updated when the pointer moves or when surface visibility, position or stacking changes affect the object under the pointer.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>WheelSpeed</name>
      <comment>Defines a multiplier to be applied to the mouse wheel.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>This field defines a multiplier applied to pointer wheel values.  A setting of <code>1.0</code> leaves wheel input unchanged, while <code>2.0</code> doubles the reported value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>X</name>
      <comment>The horizontal position of the pointer within its display.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Y</name>
      <comment>The vertical position of the pointer within its display.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>Setting <fl>X</fl> or <fl>Y</fl> on an initialised pointer forwards the change through <action>MoveToPoint</action>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="PF" comment="Flags for the Pointer class.">
      <const name="ANCHOR">Allow the pointer to be anchored.</const>
      <const name="UNUSED"/>
      <const name="VISIBLE">Indicates that the pointer is currently visible.  Read-only.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="PTC" comment="Predefined cursor styles">
      <const name="CROSSHAIR">The cross hair is used for targeting specific pixel points (common in paint programs).</const>
      <const name="CUSTOM">Works in conjunction with the SetCustomCursor() function to represent a program defined bitmap.</const>
      <const name="DEFAULT">The default cursor (usually an arrow pointing to the upper left).</const>
      <const name="DRAGGABLE">Used to indicate that a surface or object can be dragged by the user.</const>
      <const name="END"/>
      <const name="HAND">The hand cursor is often used for indicating click-able content (hyper-links, icons etc).</const>
      <const name="HAND_LEFT">Similar to the standard hand cursor, but points to the left.</const>
      <const name="HAND_RIGHT">Similar to the standard hand cursor, but points to the right.</const>
      <const name="INVISIBLE">The cursor graphic is invisible (but will continue to operate as normal in all other respects).</const>
      <const name="MAGNIFIER">Represents a magnifying glass.</const>
      <const name="NO_CHANGE"/>
      <const name="PAINTBRUSH">The paintbrush cursor is typically employed by paint programs.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_BOTTOM">Sizing cursor - for resizing the bottom edge of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_BOTTOM_LEFT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the bottom left corner of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_BOTTOM_RIGHT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the bottom right corner of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_LEFT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the left edge of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_RIGHT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the right edge of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_TOP">Sizing cursor - for resizing the top edge of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_TOP_LEFT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the top left corner of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZE_TOP_RIGHT">Sizing cursor - for resizing the top right corner of any rectangular area.</const>
      <const name="SIZING">Multi-directional sizing cursor - for resizing in any direction.</const>
      <const name="SLEEP">The sleep cursor is used to inform the user that the computer is busy.</const>
      <const name="SPLIT_HORIZONTAL">The horizontal split cursor is typically used for splitting rectangles in half, or dragging a horizontal split within a large rectangular space.</const>
      <const name="SPLIT_VERTICAL">The vertical split cursor is typically used for splitting rectangles in half, or dragging a vertical split within a large rectangular space.</const>
      <const name="STOP">The stop cursor is used to inform the user that an operation is not possible (e.g. drag and drop to an unsupported object area).</const>
      <const name="TEXT">The text cursor is popular for the precise positioning of text cursors.</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
