<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>StorageDevice</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Core</module>
    <comment>Queries metadata for file system volumes.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>b2355092</id>
    <idstring>STORAGEDEVICE</idstring>
    <category>System</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias 1996-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The StorageDevice class returns metadata for mounted file system volumes.  Set <fl>Volume</fl> before initialisation to identify the volume to query.  If the volume name cannot be resolved, initialisation will fail.</p>
<p>After initialisation, the read-only fields describe the resolved volume.  Values that depend on host or device support can remain unavailable; unknown byte counts are reported as <code>-1</code>, and <fl>DeviceID</fl> is empty if no identifier is available.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="../classes/">class_storagedevice.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>BytesFree</name>
      <comment>Amount of storage space available to the current user, measured in bytes.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT64</type>
      <description>
<p>The available storage space reported by the host file system is indicated in this field.  A value of <code>-1</code> indicates that the amount could not be determined for the selected volume.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>BytesUsed</name>
      <comment>Amount of storage space in use, measured in bytes.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT64</type>
      <description>
<p>The amount of storage space used on the volume is indicated in this field.  A value of <code>0</code> can indicate that usage could not be determined for the selected volume.</p>
<p>Please note that storage usage is typically measured in terms of blocks.  For instance, a block size of 512 bytes will mean that this field is a multiple of 512.  Two files of 1 byte each on such a file system would take up 1024 bytes of space and not 2.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DeviceFlags</name>
      <comment>These read-only flags identify the type of device and its features.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type lookup="DEVICE">DEVICE</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="DEVICE"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DeviceID</name>
      <comment>Unique device identifier for the mounted volume, when available.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
      <description>
<p>If a volume exposes a unique device identifier such as a factory serial number, it will be readable from this field. The field is empty when the selected volume or file system driver does not provide an identifier.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>DeviceSize</name>
      <comment>Total storage capacity of the resolved volume, measured in bytes.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>INT64</type>
      <description>
<p>This field indicates the total byte capacity reported by the host file system for the selected volume.  It does not reflect the remaining writable space; use <fl>BytesFree</fl> for that value.  A value of <code>-1</code> indicates that capacity could not be determined.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Volume</name>
      <comment>The volume name of the device to query.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
      <description>
<p>Set the Volume field prior to initialisation so that the object can query the selected volume.  The standard volume string format is <code>name:</code>, but omitting the colon or defining complete file system paths when writing this field is also acceptable.  Any characters following a colon are stripped automatically, and the stored value is normalised to include the trailing colon.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="DEVICE">
      <const name="BOOKMARK">This marker indicates that the presented volume is a bookmark and not a device name.</const>
      <const name="COMPACT_DISC">Compact disc style device</const>
      <const name="FIXED">Catch-all for fixed media devices that are not directly identifiable.</const>
      <const name="FLOPPY_DISK">Floppy disk style device</const>
      <const name="HARD_DISK">Hard disk style device</const>
      <const name="MEMORY">Device is RAM, ROM, WORM, NVRAM, flashdisk or other form of memory.  Does not guarantee a fast connection as it could be over a slow USB 1.1 connection for example</const>
      <const name="MODEM">Device is a modem.</const>
      <const name="NETWORK">Device represents a network link</const>
      <const name="PRINTER">Device is a paper-based printer.</const>
      <const name="PRINTER_3D">Device is a three dimensional printer.</const>
      <const name="READ">Device is readable</const>
      <const name="REMOVABLE">Device media is removable from the hardware</const>
      <const name="REMOVEABLE">Device media is removable from the hardware</const>
      <const name="SCANNER">Device is a two dimensional scanner.</const>
      <const name="SCANNER_3D">Device is a three dimensional scanner.</const>
      <const name="SOFTWARE">Device is virtual/software defined</const>
      <const name="TAPE">Tape/Stream style device</const>
      <const name="TEMPORARY">All storage is temporary</const>
      <const name="USB">Removable USB storage device.  May be further qualified by <code>HARD_DISK</code>, <code>FLOPPY_DISK</code> etc</const>
      <const name="WRITE">Device is writeable</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
