<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>Thread</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Core</module>
    <comment>Threads are created and managed by the Thread class.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>45e1cfb8</id>
    <idstring>THREAD</idstring>
    <category>System</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 1996-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The Thread class provides the means to execute and manage threads within an application.</p>
<p>The following code illustrates how to create a temporary thread that is automatically destroyed after the <code>thread_entry()</code> function has completed:</p>
<pre>static ERR thread_entry(objThread *Thread) {
   return ERR::Okay;
}

objThread::create thread = { fl::Routine(thread_entry), fl::Flags(THF::AUTO_FREE) };
if (thread.ok()) thread-&gt;activate();
</pre>
<p>To initialise the thread with data, set <fl>Data</fl> prior to execution and read the <fl>Data</fl> field from within the thread routine.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="../classes/">class_thread.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Activate</name>
      <comment>Spawn a new thread that calls the function referenced in the <fl>Routine</fl> field.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acActivate(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acActivate()</tiriPrototype>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Deactivate</name>
      <comment>Stops a thread.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acDeactivate(*Object)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acDeactivate()</tiriPrototype>
      <description>
<p>Deactivating an active thread will cause it to stop immediately.  Stopping a thread in this manner is dangerous and could result in an unstable application.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>Callback</name>
      <comment>This function will be called when the thread finishes.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>FUNCTION</type>
      <description>
<p>Set a function reference here to receive a notification when the thread finishes processing.  The callback will be executed in the context of the main program loop to minimise resource locking issues.</p>
<p>The prototype for the callback routine is <code>void Callback(objThread *Thread)</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Data</name>
      <comment>Storage for custom client data.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="W">Read/Write</access>
      <type>kt::vector&lt;int8_t&gt;</type>
      <description>
<p>The Data field is a vector of bytes that can be used to store custom data for the thread.  There are no limits associated with its use, but care should be taken if both the thread and its creator can modify its content at any time.  Reserving the size of the vector in advance is recommended if the data is to be actively shared.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Error</name>
      <comment>Reflects the error code returned by the thread routine.</comment>
      <access read="R">Read</access>
      <type>ERR</type>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Flags</name>
      <comment>Optional flags can be defined here.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="I">Read/Init</access>
      <type lookup="THF">THF</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="THF"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Routine</name>
      <comment>This function will be called when the thread starts.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>FUNCTION</type>
      <description>
<p>The routine that will be executed when the thread is activated must be specified here.  The function prototype is <code>ERR routine(objThread *Thread)</code>.</p>
<p>When the routine is called, a reference to the thread object is passed as a parameter.  Once the routine has finished processing, the resulting error code will be stored in the thread object's <fl>Error</fl> field.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="THF" comment="Thread flags">
      <const name="AUTO_FREE">Automatically destroy the Thread object when the user routine has completed.</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
