<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>VectorEllipse</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Vector</module>
    <comment>Extends the Vector class with support for elliptical path generation.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>0da60cee</id>
    <idstring>VECTORELLIPSE</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2010-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The VectorEllipse class provides the necessary functionality for elliptical path generation.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="vectors/">ellipse.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>CenterX</name>
      <comment>The horizontal center of the ellipse.  Expressed as a fixed or scaled coordinate.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The horizontal center of the ellipse is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>CenterY</name>
      <comment>The vertical center of the ellipse.  Expressed as a fixed or scaled coordinate.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The vertical center of the ellipse is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Dimensions</name>
      <comment>Dimension flags define whether individual dimension fields contain fixed or relative values.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type lookup="DMF">DMF</type>
      <description>
<p>The following dimension flags are supported:</p>
<types lookup="DMF">
<type name="FIXED_RADIUS_X">The <fl>RadiusX</fl> value is a fixed coordinate.</type>
<type name="FIXED_RADIUS_Y">The <fl>RadiusY</fl> value is a fixed coordinate.</type>
<type name="FIXED_CENTER_X">The <fl>CenterX</fl> value is a fixed coordinate.</type>
<type name="FIXED_CENTER_Y">The <fl>CenterY</fl> value is a fixed coordinate.</type>
<type name="SCALED_RADIUS_X">The <fl>RadiusX</fl> value is a scaled coordinate.</type>
<type name="SCALED_RADIUS_Y">The <fl>RadiusY</fl> value is a scaled coordinate.</type>
<type name="SCALED_CENTER_X">The <fl>CenterX</fl> value is a scaled coordinate.</type>
<type name="SCALED_CENTER_Y">The <fl>CenterY</fl> value is a scaled coordinate.</type>
</types>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Height</name>
      <comment>The height (vertical diameter) of the ellipse.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The height of the ellipse is defined here as the equivalent of <code>RadiusY * 2.0</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Radius</name>
      <comment>The radius of the ellipse.  Expressed as a fixed or scaled coordinate.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The radius of the ellipse is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.  Updating the radius will set both the <fl>RadiusX</fl> and <fl>RadiusY</fl> values simultaneously.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>RadiusX</name>
      <comment>The horizontal radius of the ellipse.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The horizontal radius of the ellipse is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>RadiusY</name>
      <comment>The vertical radius of the ellipse.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The vertical radius of the ellipse is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Vertices</name>
      <comment>Limits the total number of vertices generated for the ellipse.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Setting a value in Vertices will limit the total number of vertices that are generated for the ellipse.  This feature is useful for generating common convex geometrical shapes such as triangles, polygons, hexagons and so forth; because their vertices will always touch the sides of an elliptical area.</p>
<p>Please note that this feature is not part of the SVG standard.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Width</name>
      <comment>The width (horizontal diameter) of the ellipse.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The width of the ellipse is defined here as the equivalent of <code>RadiusX * 2.0</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="DMF">
      <const name="FIXED_CENTER_X">The CenterX field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_CENTER_Y">The CenterY field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_DEPTH">The Depth field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_HEIGHT">The Height field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_RADIUS_X">The RadiusX field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_RADIUS_Y">The RadiusY field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_WIDTH">The Width field is a fixed suze.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_X">The X field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_X_OFFSET">The XOffset field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_Y">The Y field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_Y_OFFSET">The YOffset field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_Z">The Z field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_CENTER_X">The CenterX field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_CENTER_Y">The CenterY field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_DEPTH">The Depth field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_HEIGHT">The Height field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_RADIUS_X">The RadiusX field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_RADIUS_Y">The RadiusY field is a scaled size to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_WIDTH">The Width field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_X">The X field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_X_OFFSET">The XOffset field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_Y">The Y field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_Y_OFFSET">The YOffset field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_Z">The Z field is a scaled coordinate to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="STATUS_CHANGE_H"/>
      <const name="STATUS_CHANGE_V"/>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
