<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>VectorWave</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Vector</module>
    <comment>Extends the Vector class with support for sine wave based paths.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>6d9a446f</id>
    <idstring>VECTORWAVE</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2010-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The VectorWave class provides functionality for generating paths based on sine waves.  This feature is not part of the SVG standard and therefore should not be used in cases where SVG compliance is a strict requirement.</p>
<p>The sine wave will be generated from (<fl>X</fl>,<fl>Y</fl>) across <fl>Length</fl>.  The parent view height provides the vertical region for centring and path closure, while <fl>Amplitude</fl> defines the wave height.  The path vertices are generated on a left-to-right basis.</p>
<p>Waves can be used in Kotuku's SVG implementation by using the &lt;kotuku:wave/&gt; element.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="vectors/">wave.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Move</name>
      <comment>Moves the vector to a new position.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMove(*Object, DOUBLE DeltaX, DOUBLE DeltaY, DOUBLE DeltaZ)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMove(DeltaX:num, DeltaY:num, DeltaZ:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaX">The number of units to move along the X axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaY">The number of units to move along the Y axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaZ">The number of units to move along the Z axis.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>MoveToPoint</name>
      <comment>Moves the vector to a new fixed position.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMoveToPoint(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Z, MTF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMoveToPoint(X:num, Y:num, Z:num, Flags:MTF)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="X">The new X position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Y">The new Y position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Z">The new Z position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="MTF" name="Flags" lookup="MTF">Set the relevant MTF flag for each provided parameter.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Resize</name>
      <comment>Changes the vector's length and amplitude.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acResize(*Object, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height, DOUBLE Depth)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acResize(Width:num, Height:num, Depth:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Width">The new width of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Height">The new height of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Depth">The new depth of the object.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>Amplitude</name>
      <comment>Defines the generated wave height.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>The Amplitude is expressed as a fixed or scaled value.  Fixed values are used directly, while scaled values are resolved against the parent view height.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Close</name>
      <comment>Closes the generated wave path at either the top or bottom.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type lookup="WVC">WVC</type>
      <description>
<p>Setting the Close field to <code>TOP</code> or <code>BOTTOM</code> will close the generated wave's path so that it is suitable for being filled.  This setting is not compatible with the <fl>Thickness</fl> option.</p>
<types lookup="WVC"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Decay</name>
      <comment>Declares a rate of decay to apply to the wave amplitude.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The amplitude of a wave can be decayed between its start and end points by setting the Decay field.  A value of <code>1.0</code> is the default and applies no decay.  Values between <code>0.0</code> and <code>1.0</code> set the amplitude multiplier at the end of the wave, so <code>0.5</code> tapers the wave to half amplitude and <code>0.999</code> remains visually close to no decay.  If the value is negative, the start and end points for the decay will be reversed.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Envelope</name>
      <comment>Selects the decay envelope applied to the wave amplitude.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type lookup="WVE">WVE</type>
      <description>
<p>The Envelope field controls how the <fl>Decay</fl> value is interpolated across the wave.  The default <code>LINEAR</code> envelope uses an even taper, while <code>QUADRATIC</code>, <code>SMOOTHSTEP</code> and <code>EXPONENTIAL</code> apply progressively stronger curves to the decay.</p>
<types lookup="WVE"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Frequency</name>
      <comment>Defines the wave frequency (the distance between each wave).</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The frequency determines the distance between each individual wave that is generated.  The default value for the frequency is 1.0.  Shortening the frequency to a value closer to 0 will bring the waves closer together.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Length</name>
      <comment>The horizontal length of the generated wave.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>The length of the generated wave is defined here as a fixed or scaled value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Phase</name>
      <comment>Declares the initial phase, in degrees, to use when generating the wave.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The phase value defines the initial position that is used when computing the wave.  The default is zero.</p>
<p>Visually, changing the phase will affect the 'offset' of the generated wave.  Gradually incrementing the value will give the wave an appearance of moving from right to left.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Thickness</name>
      <comment>Expands the diameter of the wave to the specified value to produce a closed path.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>Specifying a thickness value will create a wave that forms a filled shape, rather than the default of a stroked path. The thickness (diameter) of the wave is determined by the provided value.  If defined as a percentage, the value is resolved against the normalised diagonal of the parent viewport, matching the scaling rule used for #StrokeWidth. Thickness is not compatible with the <fl>Close</fl> option, and takes precedence over it.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Type</name>
      <comment>Selects an alternative wave style.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type lookup="WVT">WVT</type>
      <description>
<p>By default, waves are generated in the style of a sine wave.  Alternative styles can be selected by setting this field. The <code>SMOOTH</code> style generates a sine wave, <code>TRIANGLE</code> generates a triangular wave and <code>SAWTOOTH</code> generates a ramp with a sharp return edge.</p>
<types lookup="WVT"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>X</name>
      <comment>The x coordinate of the wave.  Can be expressed as a fixed or scaled coordinate.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>The x coordinate of the wave is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Y</name>
      <comment>The y coordinate of the wave.  Can be expressed as a fixed or scaled coordinate.</comment>
      <access read="R" write="S">Read/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>The y coordinate of the wave is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="WVC" comment="Wave options.">
      <const name="BOTTOM">Close the path across the bottom of its area.</const>
      <const name="TOP">Close the path across the top of its area.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="WVE" comment="Wave envelope options.">
      <const name="EXPONENTIAL">Exponential decay, weighted strongly towards the end of the wave.</const>
      <const name="LINEAR">Linear decay from start to end, this is the default.</const>
      <const name="QUADRATIC">Quadratic decay, weighted towards the end of the wave.</const>
      <const name="SMOOTHSTEP">Smoothstep decay with ease-in and ease-out.</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="WVT" comment="Wave style options.">
      <const name="SAWTOOTH">Sawtooth patterns rise at 45 degrees to the peak, then direct 90 degrees to the bottom.</const>
      <const name="SMOOTH">Standard sine-wave curvature, this is the default.</const>
      <const name="TRIANGLE">Chevron style angles at 45 degrees either side of the peak and bottom edge.</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
