<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>VectorPolygon</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Vector</module>
    <comment>Extends the Vector class with support for generating polygons.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>f046848b</id>
    <idstring>VECTORPOLYGON</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2010-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The VectorPolygon class provides support for three different types of vector:</p>
<list type="ordered">
<li>Closed-point polygons consisting of at least 3 points.</li>
<li>Open polygons consisting of at least 3 points (a 'polyline' in SVG).</li>
<li>Single lines consisting of two points only (a 'line' in SVG).</li>
</list>
<p>To create a polyline, set the <fl>Closed</fl> field to <code>false</code>.</p>
<p>To create a line, set the <fl>Closed</fl> field to <code>false</code> and set only two points (<fl>X1</fl>,<fl>Y1</fl>) and (<fl>X2</fl>,<fl>Y2</fl>)</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="vectors/">polygon.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <actions>
    <action>
      <name>Move</name>
      <comment>Moves a polygon to a new position.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMove(*Object, DOUBLE DeltaX, DOUBLE DeltaY, DOUBLE DeltaZ)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMove(DeltaX:num, DeltaY:num, DeltaZ:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaX">The number of units to move along the X axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaY">The number of units to move along the Y axis.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="DeltaZ">The number of units to move along the Z axis.</param>
      </input>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>MoveToPoint</name>
      <comment>Moves a polygon to a new central position.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acMoveToPoint(*Object, DOUBLE X, DOUBLE Y, DOUBLE Z, MTF Flags)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acMoveToPoint(X:num, Y:num, Z:num, Flags:MTF)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="X">The new X position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Y">The new Y position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Z">The new Z position to move the object to.</param>
        <param type="MTF" name="Flags" lookup="MTF">Set the relevant MTF flag for each provided parameter.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>This action will permanently modify the coordinates of a polygon so that they offset by the provided coordinate values.</p>
<p>The operation will abort if any of the points in the polygon are discovered to be relative coordinates.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

    <action>
      <name>Resize</name>
      <comment>Resize the polygon by its width and height.</comment>
      <prototype>ERR acResize(*Object, DOUBLE Width, DOUBLE Height, DOUBLE Depth)</prototype>
      <tiriPrototype>err = Object.acResize(Width:num, Height:num, Depth:num)</tiriPrototype>
      <input>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Width">The new width of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Height">The new height of the object.</param>
        <param type="DOUBLE" name="Depth">The new depth of the object.</param>
      </input>
      <description>
<p>This action will resize a polygon by adjusting all of its existing points.  The points are rescaled to guarantee that they are within the provided dimensions.</p>
<p>If a Width and/or Height value of zero is passed, no scaling on the associated axis will occur.</p>
      </description>
    </action>

  </actions>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>Closed</name>
      <comment>If <code>true</code>, the polygon will be closed between the start and end points.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>Set the Closed field to <code>true</code> to ensure that the polygon is closed between the start and end points.  This behaviour is the default.  If <code>false</code>, the polygon will not be closed, which results in the equivalent of the SVG polyline type.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>PathLength</name>
      <comment>Calibrates the user agent's distance-along-a-path calculations with that of the author.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>The author's computation of the total length of the path, in user units. This value is used to calibrate the user agent's own distance-along-a-path calculations with that of the author. The user agent will scale all distance-along-a-path computations by the ratio of PathLength to the user agent's own computed value for total path length.  This feature potentially affects calculations for text on a path, motion animation and various stroke operations.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Points</name>
      <comment>A series of (X,Y) coordinates that define the polygon.</comment>
      <access write="S">Set</access>
      <type>STRING</type>
      <description>
<p>The Points field can be set with a series of <code>(X, Y)</code> coordinates that will define the polygon's shape.  A minimum of two numbered pairs will be required to define a valid polygon.  Each point must be separated with either white-space or a comma.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>PointsArray</name>
      <comment>A series of numbered pairs that define the polygon.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>VectorPoint[]</type>
      <description>
<p>The PointsArray field can be set with a <st>VectorPoint</st> array that defines the shape of a polygon.  A minimum of two points is required for the shape to be valid.  The <st>VectorPoint</st> structure consists of the following fields:</p>
<struct lookup="VectorPoint"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>X1</name>
      <comment>Defines the X coordinate of the first point.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field defines the X coordinate of the first point of the polygon.  It is recommended that this field is only used when creating a VectorPolygon that will be used to draw a single line.</p>
<p>By default the value will be treated as a fixed coordinate.  Scaled values are supported if the value is a defined as a percentage.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>X2</name>
      <comment>Defines the X coordinate of the second point.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field defines the X coordinate of the second point of the polygon.  It is recommended that this field is only used when creating a VectorPolygon that will be used to draw a single line.</p>
<p>By default the value will be treated as a fixed coordinate.  Scaled values are supported if the value is a defined as a percentage.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Y1</name>
      <comment>Defines the Y coordinate of the first point.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field defines the Y coordinate of the first point of the polygon.  It is recommended that this field is only used when creating a VectorPolygon that will be used to draw a single line.</p>
<p>By default the value will be treated as a fixed coordinate.  Scaled values are supported if the value is a defined as a percentage.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Y2</name>
      <comment>Defines the Y coordinate of the second point.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>UNIT</type>
      <description>
<p>This field defines the Y coordinate of the second point of the polygon.  It is recommended that this field is only used when creating a VectorPolygon that will be used to draw a single line.</p>
<p>By default the value will be treated as a fixed coordinate.  Scaled values are supported if the value is a defined as a percentage.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <structs>
    <struct name="VectorPoint" comment="Structure for the VectorPolygon PointsArray field.">
      <field name="X" type="DOUBLE">The X coordinate of this point.</field>
      <field name="Y" type="DOUBLE">The Y coordinate of this point.</field>
      <field name="XScaled" type="UINT8"><code>TRUE</code> if the <code>X</code> value is scaled to its viewport (between 0 and 1.0).</field>
      <field name="YScaled" type="UINT8"><code>TRUE</code> if the <code>Y</code> value is scaled to its viewport (between 0 and 1.0).</field>
    </struct>

  </structs>
</book>
