<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="class.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>VectorSpiral</name>
    <type>class</type>
    <module>Vector</module>
    <comment>Extends the Vector class with support for spiral path generation.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <id>a86a1429</id>
    <idstring>VECTORSPIRAL</idstring>
    <category>Graphics</category>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2010-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>The VectorSpiral class generates spiral paths that extend from a central point.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="vectors/">spiral.cpp</file>
    </source>
  </info>

  <fields>
    <field>
      <name>CenterX</name>
      <comment>The horizontal center of the spiral.  Expressed as a fixed or scaled coordinate.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The horizontal center of the spiral is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>CenterY</name>
      <comment>The vertical center of the spiral.  Expressed as a fixed or scaled coordinate.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The vertical center of the spiral is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Dimensions</name>
      <comment>Dimension flags define whether individual dimension fields contain fixed or relative values.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type lookup="DMF">DMF</type>
      <description>
<types lookup="DMF"/>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Height</name>
      <comment>The height (vertical diameter) of the spiral.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The height of the spiral is expressed as <code>Radius * 2.0</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>LoopLimit</name>
      <comment>Used to limit the number of loops produced by the spiral path generator.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The LoopLimit can be used to impose a limit on the total number of loops that are performed by the spiral path generator.  It can be used as an alternative to, or conjunction with the <fl>Radius</fl> value to limit the final spiral size.</p>
<p>If the LoopLimit is not set, the <fl>Radius</fl> will take precedence.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Offset</name>
      <comment>Offset the starting coordinate of the spiral by this value.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The generation of a spiral's path can be offset by specifying a positive value in the Offset field.  By default the Offset is set to zero.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>PathLength</name>
      <comment>Calibrates the user agent's distance-along-a-path calculations with that of the author.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>INT</type>
      <description>
<p>The author's computation of the total length of the path, in user units. This value is used to calibrate the user agent's own distance-along-a-path calculations with that of the author. The user agent will scale all distance-along-a-path computations by the ratio of PathLength to the user agent's own computed value for total path length.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Radius</name>
      <comment>The radius of the spiral.  Expressed as a fixed or scaled coordinate.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The radius of the spiral is defined here as either a fixed or scaled value.  If zero, preference is given to <fl>LoopLimit</fl>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Spacing</name>
      <comment>Declares the amount of empty space between each loop of the spiral.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>Spacing tightly controls the computation of the spiral path, ensuring that a specific amount of empty space is left between each loop.  The space is declared in pixel units.</p>
<p>If Spacing is undeclared, the spiral expands at an incremental rate of <code>Step * 0.1</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Step</name>
      <comment>Determines the distance between each vertex in the spiral's path.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The Step value affects the distance between each vertex in the spiral path during its generation.  The default value is <code>1.0</code>.  Using larger values will create a spiral with jagged corners due to the reduction in vertices.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

    <field>
      <name>Width</name>
      <comment>The width (horizontal diameter) of the spiral.</comment>
      <access read="G" write="S">Get/Set</access>
      <type>DOUBLE</type>
      <description>
<p>The width of the spiral is expressed as <code>Radius * 2.0</code>.</p>
      </description>
    </field>

  </fields>
  <types>
    <constants lookup="DMF">
      <const name="FIXED_CENTER_X">The CenterX field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_CENTER_Y">The CenterY field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_DEPTH">The Depth field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_HEIGHT">The Height field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_RADIUS_X">The RadiusX field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_RADIUS_Y">The RadiusY field is a fixed size.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_WIDTH">The Width field is a fixed suze.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_X">The X field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_X_OFFSET">The XOffset field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_Y">The Y field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_Y_OFFSET">The YOffset field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="FIXED_Z">The Z field is a fixed coordinate.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_CENTER_X">The CenterX field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_CENTER_Y">The CenterY field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_DEPTH">The Depth field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_HEIGHT">The Height field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_RADIUS_X">The RadiusX field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_RADIUS_Y">The RadiusY field is a scaled size to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_WIDTH">The Width field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_X">The X field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_X_OFFSET">The XOffset field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_Y">The Y field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_Y_OFFSET">The YOffset field is scaled to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="SCALED_Z">The Z field is a scaled coordinate to this object's parent.</const>
      <const name="STATUS_CHANGE_H"/>
      <const name="STATUS_CHANGE_V"/>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
