<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="module.xsl"?>

<book>
  <info>
    <name>Tiri</name>
    <type>module</type>
    <comment>Tiri is a customised scripting language for the Script class.</comment>
    <version>1</version>
    <status>stable</status>
    <prefix>ti</prefix>
    <copyright>Paul Manias © 2006-2026</copyright>
    <description>
<p>Tiri is a custom scripting language for Kotuku developers.  It is implemented on the backbone of LuaJIT, a high performance version of the Lua scripting language.  It supports garbage collection, dynamic typing and a 64-bit byte-code interpreter for compiled code.</p>
<p>Tiri files use the <code>.tiri</code> file extension.  Ideally, scripts should start with the comment '-- $TIRI' near the start of the document so that it can be correctly identified by the Tiri class.</p>
<p>For more information on the Tiri syntax, please refer to the official Tiri Reference Manual.</p></description>
    <source>
      <file path="src/tiri/">tiri.cpp</file>
    </source>
    <classes>
      <class>Tiri</class>
    </classes>
  </info>

  <function>
    <name>SetVariable</name>
    <comment>Sets any variable in a loaded Tiri script.</comment>
    <prototype>ERR ti::SetVariable(objTiri * Script, STRVIEW Name, INT Type, ...)</prototype>
    <tiriPrototype>err = SetVariable(Script:obj, Name:str, Type:num, ...)</tiriPrototype>
    <tags>mutates-object, copies-input</tags>
    <input>
      <param type="objTiri *" name="Script">Pointer to a Tiri script.</param>
      <param type="STRVIEW" name="Name">The name of the variable to set.</param>
      <param type="INT" name="Type">A valid field type must be indicated, e.g. <code>FD_STRING</code>, <code>FD_POINTER</code>, <code>FD_INT</code>, <code>FD_DOUBLE</code>, <code>FD_INT64</code>.</param>
      <param type="..." name="Variable">A variable that matches the indicated <code>Type</code>.</param>
    </input>
    <description>
<p>The SetVariable() function provides a method for setting global variables in a Tiri script prior to execution of that script.  If the script is cached, the variable settings will be available on the next activation.</p>
    </description>
    <result type="ERR">
      <error code="Okay">The variable was defined successfully.</error>
      <error code="Args">Invalid arguments passed to function</error>
      <error code="ObjectCorrupt">Privately maintained memory has become inaccessible.</error>
      <error code="FieldTypeMismatch">A valid field type was not specified in the <code>Type</code> parameter.</error>
      <error code="InvalidState">The script does not have an active Tiri state.</error>
    </result>
  </function>

  <types>
    <constants lookup="JET" comment="JET constants are documented in GetInputEvent()">
      <const name="ABS_XY">The X, Y values are defined as absolute coordinates, relative to the top-left of the display</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_1">Left mouse button; XBox A button, PS square button.  Value is pressure sensitive, ranging between 0 - 1.0 (0 is released, 1.0 is fully depressed)</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_10">Non-specific button assignment</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_2">Right mouse button; XBox X button, PS cross button</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_3">Middle mouse button; XBox Y button, PS triangle</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_4">Alt. mouse button 1; XBox B button, PS circle</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_5">Alt. mouse button 2</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_6">Non-specific button assignment</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_7">Non-specific button assignment</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_8">Non-specific button assignment</const>
      <const name="BUTTON_9">Non-specific button assignment</const>
      <const name="CROSSED_IN">This message is sent by the input system when the mouse pointer enters an area for the first time.  The message value refers to the object ID of the container being monitored for movement</const>
      <const name="CROSSED_OUT">This message is sent by the input system when the mouse pointer leaves an area.  The message value refers to the object ID of the container being monitored for movement</const>
      <const name="DEVICE_TILT_XY">Controller tilted on the X/Y axis.  Value indicates angle, -ve = left, +ve = right</const>
      <const name="DEVICE_TILT_Z">Controller is rising or falling.  Value expressed as 'speed',</const>
      <const name="DISPLAY_EDGE">Recently supplied input occurred at the edge of the display</const>
      <const name="PEN_TILT_XY">Pen tilt angle.  0 is pointing down directly with nib at bottom, 0.5 is 90 degrees, 1.0 is inversed (eraser at bottom)</const>
      <const name="PRESSURE">Amount of pressure applied, ranges from 0 (none) to 1.0 (normal) and possibly higher if user presses hard enough</const>
      <const name="WHEEL">Mouse wheel rotation - the value generally reflects the number of 'clicks' rotated on the wheel</const>
      <const name="WHEEL_TILT">Some mouse wheels can be tilted to the left or right.  Ranges from -1.0 to +1.0</const>
    </constants>

    <constants lookup="JTYPE" comment="JTYPE flags are used to categorise input types">
      <const name="ANALOG">Analog movement (ranging from -1.0 to 1.0)</const>
      <const name="ANCHORED">Cursor has been anchored with LockCursor()</const>
      <const name="BUTTON">Input is a physical button or switch</const>
      <const name="CROSSING">Crossing events manage the entering and leaving of an area</const>
      <const name="DBL_CLICK">Set by the input system if the <code>Type</code> is a button and the button has been clicked in quick succession so as to be classed as a double-click</const>
      <const name="DIGITAL">D-Pad or digital joystick source (restricted to +/- 1)</const>
      <const name="DRAGGED">Set if sufficient movement occurred between the original click and its point of release (usually requires a 3 or more pixel difference)</const>
      <const name="DRAG_ITEM">This special flag is set by the input system if the pointer is click-dragging an object at the time of the event</const>
      <const name="EXT_MOVEMENT">Extended or indirect movement information.  This covers all types of movement that are unconnected to coordinate positioning -  mouse wheel movement and pen tilt are two such examples</const>
      <const name="MOVEMENT">X/Y coordinate movement only. Movement such as the wheel mouse spinning is not covered by this type as it does not influence the coordinate system</const>
      <const name="REPEATED">Input is a repeated entry (i.e. user is holding down a button and a repetition timer is being triggered)</const>
      <const name="SECONDARY">Indicates to the receiver of this message that it is not the primary/original recipient</const>
    </constants>

  </types>
  <structs>
  </structs>
</book>
